Richar Orlando Melo

Career Summary

Software engineer with more than five years of experience in the software development cycle, as well as domain of the Java back-end programming language. Experience working with SCRUM methodology. I have been part of five projects teams for the car brand, insurance, banking, marketing and healthcare sectors. In the last year I worked on refactoring from a legacy monolithic architecture to a new one using cloud AWS technologies like serverless and frameworks like spring boot.

Summary of Qualifications

Skills:

- Java
- Spring boot
- Javascript
- Typescript
- Junit/Mockito
- Angular/Ionic
- Oracle
- PostgreSQL
- PL/SOL
- Docker
- Maven
- Gradle
- AWS
- Terraform

Nov. 2022 – At date

- Linux
- Git

Languages

• Spanish (native speaker)

English (intermediate)

Career History

Mercadolibre, Bogotá, Colombia

Back-end Developer

- Maintained and improved the "Dependency Catalog" initiative, managing a comprehensive inventory of over 500 dependencies used across Mercadolibre's projects.
- Implemented the Circuit Breaker pattern, ensuring 99.9% uptime for the Dependency Catalog by mitigating failures during integration with various external APIs.
- Developed and deployed an API for managing vulnerabilities, enabling the creation and tracking of issues related to known vulnerabilities in cataloged libraries.
- Reduced platform downtime by 25% through the implementation of a dual-approval system for dependency updates, enhancing application security and stability.
- Utilized Fury, Mercadolibre's internal tool, to integrate and manage the application ecosystem, facilitating interoperability and efficient handling of dependencies across the organization.

Globant, Bogotá, Colombia

Jun. 2021 – Nov. 2022

Back-end Developer

- Build first mvp for an automotive industry application for Nissan-MX.
- Coordinated with frontend and product teams in the identification of the services that provide
- consume and use external services such as telemetry to integrate with the mobile application.
- Assist in the definition and design of the backend architecture in the cloud with aws for the Nissan mobile application.

Sophos Solutions - ADL, Bogotá, Colombia

Back-end Developer

- Migrated specific microservices and serverless modules on the predefined AWS architecture
- Create infrastructure as code of specific modules for the migration project
- Assist in the definition and design of the architecture of the migration project modules
- Coordinated with engineering and product teams in identification of the migration project
- A security library was created across all laboratory services

PSL Corp, Bogotá, Colombia

Nov. 2019 - Jul. 2020

Nov. 2020 - May. 2021

Back-end Developer

- Developed new functionalities and maintained existing ones on an application for different marketing channels
- Suggest technical and efficient solutions to the client's needs.
- Implementation of a new module in the application used by a Health company to manage the information of its affiliates
- Assist that the development team implements the best coding practices. (Peer review, CI)

Banco de Bogotá, Bogotá, Colombia

Jun. 2019 - Oct. 2019

Back-end Developer

- Developed mobile, web and cloud infrastructure of the post-sales offices of the bank's services
- Developed mobile, web and cloud infrastructure of digital shifts of all the bank's headquarters nationwide
- Improvement on waiting time in branches to solve post-sales services, increasing customer satisfaction measured by NPS indicators vs traditional services

S4N, Bogotá, Colombia

Apr. 2018 - May. 2019

Back-end Developer

- Developed an application for internal client based on microservices for all pension modalities nationwide according to current legislation
- Designed and created distributed applications that are flexible and are able to scale in demand through reactive technologies and the functional paradigm
- Refined performance and tracked the life cycle of the modules form the development stages to production

Education

Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia MS, Information Security

Aug. 2022 – At date

Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Bogotá, Colombia BS, Systems and Computer Engineering

Feb. 2012 - Jun. 2018